<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="style_xml.css" type="text/css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title ref="https://puppetplays.eu/oeuvres/245937/politicks-in-miniature">Politicks in Miniature</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="MSK">Maxine Schoehuys-Kreiss</name>
          <resp ref="maxine.schoehuys-kreiss@univ-montp3.fr">Edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="CD">Cécile Decaix</name>
          <resp>Transcription and edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <principal ref="didier.plassard@univ-montp3.fr" xml:id="DP">Didier Plassard</principal>
        <sponsor>PuppetPlays project (ERC GA 835193)</sponsor>
        <funder>European Research Council - ERC</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor ref="https://books.google.fr/books?id=yHZZAAAAcAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">Google Books</distributor>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence>Public domain</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="DOI"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Un membre du gouvernement démissionne</note>
        <note>Politicks in Miniature (la politique en miniature) fait la
          satire de l’homme politique Robert Walpole qui, à la tête de la Chambre des
          Communes, jouait un rôle similaire à celui de Premier ministre. Le texte a été
          imprimé dans un numéro du Westminster Journal de 1741, de façon
          anonyme, et son auteur n'a pas pu être identifié. L’avant-propos
          qui précède le texte utilise la métaphore répandue du theatrum mundi
          qui compare le monde à une scène de théâtre. Ici, le gouvernement est représenté
          comme une troupe de théâtre de marionnettes dont Punch est à la tête. Le personnage
          qu’il incarne rappelle Robert Walpole, l'homme politique du parti Whig
          (conservateur). L’intrigue se situe dans un contexte politique bien particulier et
          reflète la chute de Walpole. En 1741, lors des élections générales britanniques, le
          gouvernement Walpole est affaibli, même s’il conserve une mince majorité. L’année
          suivante, Walpole se voit contraint de poser sa démission suite à une motion de
          censure qui renverse son gouvernement. La pièce a été mise en scène à
          Londres, au Old Theatre près de Pall Mall, avec de grandes marionnettes
          ("rich and large figures"). Dans la plupart des éditions, le texte
          de Politicks in Miniature est suivi d'une arlequinade elle aussi
          satirique, The Political Rehearsal - Harlequin Le Grand : Or, the Tricks of
          Pierrot le Primier (sic), mais celle-ci semble plutôt destinée à des
          acteurs.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <personGrp role="audience">
            <p>Non spécifié</p>
          </personGrp>
        </listPerson>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>British Library. 1486.b.14</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <p>Number of pages in the original document: 15</p>
                <p>Number of acts in the original document: 5</p>
                <p>Format of the original document: Imprimé</p>
              </objectDesc>
            </physDesc>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
        <bibl>
          <title type="main"
            ref="https://books.google.fr/books?id=yHZZAAAAcAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">Politicks in Miniature</title>
          <title type="sub">Or, the Humours of Punch's Resignation</title>
          <title type="alt">The State Puppet-Show: called the Humours of Punch's
            Resignation.</title>
          <date>1741</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="">Anglais</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords source="animationTechniques">
          <term source="https://puppetplays.eu/techniques-d-animation/1217/marionnette-à-tringle-et-fils">Marionnette à tringle et à fils</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="literaryTones">
          <term/>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="theatricalTechniques">
          <term>Annonce publique</term>
          <term>Allusion à l'actualité politique</term>
          <term>Scène de complot</term>
          <term>Accent étranger comique</term>
          <term>Épilogue</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="genre">
          <term>A Tragi-Comi-Farcical-Operatical Puppet-Show. With a new scene of Punch's Levee,
            and the surprising metamorphosis of his puppets</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="keywords">
          <term>Complot</term>
          <term>Politique</term>
          <term>Manipulation</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>The semi-diplomatic norms applied are intended to guide and facilitate the reading of the original texts. The transcriptions therefore include spelling and grammatical corrections according to current standards.</p>
          <p>The author's orthographic and grammatical corrections have been integrated into the text without being marked. Cuts for performance purposes have not been adopted in the transcription.</p>
          <p>Syntax has been modernised where it is naturally incorrect or has become incomprehensible today. Additions are limited and indicated by square brackets.</p>
          <p>The copyist's obvious errors (scene numbers, character attributions, etc.) have been corrected. The list of characters could also be corrected.</p>
        </normalization>
        <punctuation marks="some">
          <p>Punctuation has been corrected according to modern rules.</p>
        </punctuation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text collected during the PuppetPlays project funded by European Union (Grant
          Agreement 835193) under Horizon 2020. The PuppetPlays project aims to
          re-evaluate the contribution of the puppets repertoire to the construction of
          European cultural identity. Its main goals is to collect a corpus of
          representative plays from Western Europe (Germany, Austria, Belgium, Spain,
          France, Great Britain, Italy, Netherlands, Portugal, Switzerland) between the
          17th and the 21th century. It also tries to identify the characteristics of
          puppet dramaturgy and their variations depending on eras, cultural spheres,
          producing conditions, and the aimed public.</p>
        <p>This edition is the result of university research work, reviewed by the principal investigator.</p>
        <p>This transcription and the editorial work are distributed under the <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"> Creative
          Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA)
        </ref> licence. This license enables reusers to distribute, remix, adapt, and
          build upon the material in any medium or format for non-commercial purposes
          only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator. If you remix,
          adapt, or build upon the material, you must license the modified material under
          identical terms. </p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when-iso="2025-09-18" who="#MSK">TEI Header created from a JSON extraction of the PuppetPlays' database.</change>
      <change when-iso="2024" who="#CD">Transcription and encoding of the text.</change>
      <change when-iso="2025-07-01" who="#MSK">Encoding revision.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb n="1" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_01.jpg"/>
      <docTitle>
        <titlePart type="main">Politicks in Miniature : Or, The Humours of Punch’s
          Resignation.</titlePart>
      </docTitle>
      <docEdition>Anon., Politicks in Miniature. London: J. Mechell</docEdition>
      <docDate>1741</docDate>
      <pb n="2" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_02.jpg"/>
      <!-- <docEdition>A Tragi-Comi-Farcical-Operatical Puppet-Show. With A New Scene of Punch’s
                Levee, and the Surprising Metamorphosis of his Puppets. To which is added, <em>The
                    Political Rehearsal. Harlequin Le Grand : Or, the Tricks of Pierrot le
                    Primier.</em> With <em>The Cheats and Adventures of Punchinello, Mezotin,
                    Scaramouch, Pantaloon, and others.</em> Being, A Tragi-Comi-Pantomimical
                Performance Of two acts. In which are introduced A heroic scene of femal honour, and
                a Very majestic pantomime scene of kicking. The whole interspersed with, Patriots,
                chorus of patriots ; courtiers, chorus Of courtiers ; songs ; observations, critical
                and Political. </docEdition>
                <div>
                <p>Taken from the Westminster journal of March 20, 1741-42, Oct. 30, and Nov. 6,
                    1742. </p>
                <p>From my lodgings in Spring-Gardens.</p>
                <lg>
                    <l><foreign xml:lang="la">Totus Mundus agit Histrionem – Ligneum</foreign></l>
                    <l><foreign xml:lang="lat">Totus Mundus agit Histrionem – Ligneum</foreign></l>
                </lg>
                <p>That all the world is a stage-play, and all men are merely players, is a
                    reflection as just as it is common. The similitude may be carried farther, by
                    comparing it to a farce, in which the scenes have more of the ridiculous ; and,
                    I think, yet farther, if we fall in the sentiments of my following
                    correspondent, who sent me a scene of a puppet-show/ - I can say no more of
                    where it was performed, or who are the <foreign xml:lang="lat">dramatis
                        personae</foreign>, than Mr. Gay explains of the Secret History of
                    What-d’ye-call-it,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>There is a meaning in it, and no doubt </l>
                    <l>You all have sense enough to find it out.</l>
                </lg>

            </div>-->
      <castList>
        <head type="personnage">[Cast list</head>
        <castItem>
          <role>Master,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Punch,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>The Red Puppet,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Puppet Carlo,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Staunch,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Puppat Lawn,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Puppet Freeman,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Puppet Merit,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Puppet Winni,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Puppet H—ce,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Puppet Y—,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Captain Caledon,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Mr English,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Mr Worcester,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Puppet Will's wife]</role>
        </castItem>
      </castList>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="1">
        <pb n="3" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_03.jpg"/>
        <head type="titre">Politics in Miniature:</head>
        <div type="3">
          <head type="scene" n="1">Scene 1</head>
          <head type="nameS">Master of the puppet-show and Punch</head>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Vhat, Master Punch, make you in such passion ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Z—ns ! All the puppets are in confederacy against me. — There are plots ; — plots in
              the State, Sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Plots ! Vhat you call plots, Master Punch ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>I’ll tell you what I call plots. — You know I have been the hero of the stage for
              twenty years : I have acted the principal parts, I have diverted the public with
              several ingenious pranks, made heroic and witty speeches, knocked down those puppets
              that affronted me, kicked those off the stage that contradicted me, introduced those
              that complimented me. This have I reigned, with distinguished lustre, at the head of
              your company of wooden politicians.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Vary vell, Master Punch, but vere be dis grand plot ? You have often talked of de
              plat, and de plot, but vere be dis plot ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>There are parties formed against me, and some of the puppets have been bold enough to
              say that I should not be at the head of the c[o]mpany any longer.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Be dis de plot ! — Dis is only against <stage type="corps">you</stage>. I tought
              against <stage type="corps">me</stage> dat it was laid by mine puppets.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Why, have I not told you [a] hundred times, that is the very same thing. Witness ye
              Gods ! That through my sides they strike at you : they look on all my actions as
              yours, they know I move and have my being from you, and whatever part I play, it is
              with <stage type="corps">your</stage> consent.</p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="4" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_04.jpg"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Very true. But if I command you to <stage type="corps">say dis</stage>, or <stage
                type="corps">do dat</stage>, shall rascally damned puppets contradict me ? Don’t dey
              know dat I hold de strings dat move dem about on de stage ? Dat it is I speak what you
              s[p]eak out ? Dat —</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>But, Sir, they say that they have felt a new kind if inspiration ; and that some God,
              or other, has endued them with new faculties and powers, and that they can speak and
              act upon new principles. Therefore, in the scenes they now play, you are to look on
              them not as mere pieces of wood, but as real characters.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Oh ! Ho ! —Den dat — (vat you call !)— dat inspiration be de plot. And all mine
              puppet in dis plot ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>No, no : I have a strong party, as you will see soon. If you will sit down here
              behind the screen, you shall see such scenes played among your puppets, as will be an
              arrant droll.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>And who move de strings all dis time ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>You are not to imagine them wooden figures. Be a spectator of real representation,
              and I will begin the farce. — Whenever you think proper of speaking with us, it must
              be behind the screen. — </p>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Exit</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>—Vary vell ! — Mine show house is full of spectators : the curtain draws up, and —ha
              ! Ha ! Enter Master Punch for de prologue.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Enter Punch</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Britons attend ! — nor haughtily disdain, </l>
              <l>To view the actions of out mimic scene ; </l>
              <l>A group of various characters it brings, </l>
              <l>All statesmen, and all moved by secret springs. </l>
              <l>In fiction’s guise we real truths rehearse ; </l>
              <l>The world, and the world’s rulers prove a farce : </l>
              <l>Nor statesmen, dare our statesmen here despise ; </l>
              <l>As you they’re honest, and as you they’re wise. </l>
              <l>But, laying tragic rants aside, you see </l>
              <l>The comic her[o] of the show in me. </l>
              <l>In me behold him who never had his fellow, </l>
              <l>Enabled by the title Punchinello.</l>
              <pb n="5" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_05.jpg"/>
              <l>Long over the stage I’ve bore tyrannic sway, </l>
              <l>And made the puppet herd power obey ; </l>
              <l>I blustered, laughed, swore, swaggered, kicked, and then, </l>
              <l>In humblest mood I took some kicks again. </l>
              <l>But now behold me in an odder station, </l>
              <l>Playing the farce of statesman’s resignation, </l>
              <l>A scene I still shall do less good than hurt in, </l>
              <l>Then bid you kiss my —, and drop the curtain.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Exit Punch</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>O rare Punch, dat vas admirably vel spoke. —Now de scene opens with Punch’s puppets.
              Dere be de Cockade puppets, de Blue, de Green, de Red, de Black and Vite — Vat you
              call dis scene, Master Punch ?</p>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Scene discovers Punch at his levee of puppets.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>This is the levee. — Though there is though to be much art required to play this
              scene, it is not more than a woman of common beauty does every day in the drawing
              room.</p>
            <stage type="saut">Song</stage>
            <lg>
              <l>The Coquette, encircled round </l>
              <l>With the fops she deigns to wound, </l>
              <l>Shows the wisdom of the fair, </l>
              <l>Smiling here, and ogling there ; </l>
              <l>Raising hope, by kindly glancing ; </l>
              <l>Seeming favours now advancing ; </l>
              <l>All in turns expect the blessing ; </l>
              <l>All insured of the possessing : </l>
              <l>But the sly maid, at Love’s true call, </l>
              <l>To some fond creature of her heart, </l>
              <l>Who most she thinks can love impart, </l>
              <l>Glad gives her hand, and jilts them all. </l>
              <l>Like the art of the Coquette, </l>
              <l>Is our conduct in the State ; </l>
              <l>Circled by a hundred round, </l>
              <l>Hundred little arts are found ; </l>
              <l>Here by bowing, there assuring ; </l>
              <l>Here by whipping, there alluring ;</l>
              <pb n="6" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_06.jpg"/>
              <l>All expect the favour granted ; </l>
              <l>All sure of the place they wanted, </l>
              <l>But find, mistaken in their friend, </l>
              <l>The Stateman never favour gave, </l>
              <l>But like the woman to the slave, </l>
              <l>Who best he thought could serve his end.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>This has been my maxim from my coming into power, and I will retain it to my going
              out of it. Among all these there may not be five but may wish me hanged, if it was not
              their interest to have me at the head of them – and that can’t be long ; therefore I
              must manage them with all the art I am master of.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Punch comes from the side scene towards the puppets, bowing very low to
            them, and they all with many cringes return the compliment.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <stage type="pers">(to a red puppet)</stage>
            <p>I don’t remember, Sir, ever to have seen you <stage type="corps">here</stage>
              before.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet</speaker>
            <p>No, Sir, my command in the army prevented me : as I was a Lieutenant-Colonel of a
              Regiment, I thought it was my duty to be with it, while my Colonel was attending your
              Honour, and the business of P—rl—t.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>I suppose then, good Sir, you have now a seat in the House, and have left the command
              to the Major, or senior Captain, or Brigadier, or Sub-Brigadier, or —or—somebody or
              other.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet</speaker>
            <p>No, Sir, I have no seat in the House : my affair is this. My Colonel is dead : I have
              been Lieutenant Colonel above thirty years, and in the service near fifty : I am come
              to solicit for this vacant Regiment, as my long and faithful services to my King and
              country may plead in my favour. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Service to you King and country, Sir ? — What services, Sir ? — Why you have no seat
              in the House, Sir :—I thought you might have had a seat in the House, I can’t do
              anything in your affair, Sir. — Nay, I don’t know but the Regiment is disposed of.
                —<stage type="corps">(Turns his heel from him.)</stage>Ask for a Regiment, and no
              member : the fellow’s mad sure !<stage type="corps">To a Ducal Puppet at his
                elbow</stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="7" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_07.jpg"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>The Red Puppet</speaker>
            <stage type="saut">retiring</stage>
            <lg>
              <l>This is just as I was told. </l>
              <l>Hence vile reproach sullies the soldier’s fame, </l>
              <l>And as corruption’s minion brands his name : </l>
              <l>Rough, and experienced in war’s honoured art, </l>
              <l>Their tongue unguileful, and unstained their heart, </l>
              <l>Our fathers served their country and their King ; </l>
              <l>But modern G—n’ r—ls modern talents bring : </l>
              <l>Hence Vice our honest soldier’s fame destroys, </l>
              <l>Ensigns are Senators, and G—n’ R—ls Boys.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Exit</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <stage type="saut">to a puppet with a star on his breast.</stage>
            <p>And does your Grace really think of going into the army ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet M</speaker>
            <p>I am determined on it. — I will be a soldier.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>A soldier ! No, no, your grace shall be no soldier. — you shall be a General. — There
              is a regiment luckily just vacant.— I have been solicited for it, but — I am glad I
              have an opportunity to offer it your Grace.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet</speaker>
            <p>I am your Honour’s most humble, and most obedient servant. —I shall endeavour to
              return the favour. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>I don’t doubt it. <stage type="corps">(To another puppet.)</stage> O ! Your servant,
              Mr Staunch. — A word with you. —I don’t know what to do about what you requested of me
              —for—</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet</speaker>
            <p>For what ? I am surprised at any demurs : I never asked anything for myself. — I
              could not have thought after the services I have done you such a trifle —</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Don’t mistake me : I recommended your son to the board for a Fifty-Gun Ship, but was
              answered he had not been a Lieutenant above a year : — What could I s[a]y ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet</speaker>
            <p>What you would have said had you had a mind it should be done.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Well, Mr Staunch, I would not have you out of humour : your son shall be commissioned
              as you desire : you shall be convinced of it now. <stage type="corps">(Calls a
                puppet.)</stage> Chevalier Carolo, Mr Staunch’s son is, I hear, a very pretty fellow
              in the Navy : is there any Fifty-Gun Ship vacant ?</p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="8" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_08.jpg"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Carolo</speaker>
            <p>Not at present ; but we shall commission some next week for that secret expedition
              you talked of.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>O ! very well : give Mr Staunch the first Fifty-Gun Ship you name.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Carolo</speaker>
            <p>It shall be done.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Staunch</speaker>
            <p>I thank your Honour ; I knew your Honour’s power if you would exert it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>You’ll be at the House, Staunch ; we shall have warm work.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Staunch</speaker>
            <p>Never doubt me, your Honour’s servant.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Plague on it, here comes a right R—vr—d Dun, which of all court duns is the most
              troublesome and insatiable.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Lawn</speaker>
            <p>I beg your Honour’s pardon for not waiting on you as soon as I came from my diocese
              but I have been laid up with a fit of the gout.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>French wine and champagne, my Lord, have strange effects, ho ! ho ! ho !</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Lawn</speaker>
            <p>Your Honour pleases to be merry, but in truth this election affair did compel me to
              exceed a little : I love, if I serve my friend, to serve him with spirit and
              truth.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Then you serve your friend better than you do your G—. <stage type="corps"
                >(Aside)</stage> I hear, my Lord, that you remarkably distinguished yourself by your
              zeal.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Lawn</speaker>
            <p>Sir, I exercised my pastoral authority over my flock, and dispersed circular letter
              to order them how they should vote : I have been threatened by the faction on this
              account, but I esteem myself safe enough under your Honour’s protection.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>My Lord, you have not much to apprehend : some silly fellows may indeed say that you
              did not act becoming a member of the Church, that you were one of my tools, that you
              were a mercenary priest, and that your robes ought to be striped over your ears.
              Perhaps too you may be obliged to ask somebody pardon on your knees. But what’s all
              this ? When ‘tis over you may bid them all kiss your a—.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Lawn</speaker>
            <p>Ha ! ha ! ha ! Your Honour’s witty. <pb n="9"
                facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_09.jpg"/> —But, please your Honour, I have
              news to tell you. — My Lord of —, who, you know, was of the other Party, was given
              over this morning by his physicians. I am sorry for my brother of — : he was a good
              sort of a man, but had not a right way of thinking it politics.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>And pray what honest fellow do you know of to succeed him.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Lawn</speaker>
            <p>Why, —Umph ! —Why, —ha ! ha ! ha ! — Your Honour knows that See is two thousand a
              year more than mine. — If your Honour thinks me a tolerably honest fellow. —Ha ! ha !
              ha ! —I know your Honour likes a joke.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>I’ll tell you, my Lord, whoever has that B—ck, must make a free-will offering of five
              thousand pounds to a certain female saint. If your Lordship’s orthodoxy can allow this
              this Saint Worship, I shall. Think you an honest fellow enough. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Lawn</speaker>
            <stage type="pers">(to himself)</stage>
            <p>Five thousand for two thousand a year : —two years and a half pays the purchase
              money. — I am forty-six ; —may live twenty or thirty years longer : — say seventy :
              —that’s twenty-four : —that’s twenty-eight thousand pounds for five. —Please your
              Honour your Saint may be assured of my devotion and offering.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>And you of the B—k.<stage type="corps">(Aside)</stage> Well, this will buy Polly a
              pair of earrings. Oh ! Your servant, Mr Freeman, I did not see you before : have you
              been with P—x—n ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Freeman</speaker>
            <p>Yes, please your Honour.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>And he has given you those papers of hints and instructions ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Freeman</speaker>
            <p>Yes, Sir.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Pray take care and write stronger : lash those factious tumultuous set of fellows,
              the C—t-zens of L—n : lay about you as if you were [i]n earnest.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Freeman</speaker>
            <p>I shall obey your honour’s commands.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>I have given P—-x—n a draught of fifteen hundred pounds for you : but out of it you
              must give <pb n="10" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_10.jpg"/> the fellow a
              hundred, who wrote the letter to a Member of Parliament. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Freeman</speaker>
            <p>I will, Sir. —Damn your temper. — <stage type="corps">(Aside)</stage> Even in your
              extravagance you can’t forbear your old trick of quartering.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Have you any business with me, Sir ? Or is this only a visit of compliment ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet</speaker>
            <p>Sir, my name is Merit.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Merit ! Merit ! — I don’t know you. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet</speaker>
            <p>I was recommended to you by Doctor Galen.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Oh ! You are the Cambridge man that is going to print some learned expensive
              work.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet</speaker>
            <p>Which I hope to have the honour to inscribe to your patronage.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Sir, these works of learning are of no use to me : I must be excused, you may find a
              more proper patron ; but as I love to encourage learned men, there’s a guinea for you.
                <stage type="corps">(Turns from him and goes on, followed by the other
                puppets.)</stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Merit</speaker>
            <stage type="corps">Solus</stage>
            <p>A Guinea ! —A single guinea ! —What a wretch ! —</p>
            <lg>
              <l>From these cursed walls with terror I will fly, </l>
              <l>Where arts and science never come nigh : </l>
              <l>Where the mean Sycophant, or venal slave, </l>
              <l>Rival the honest, and supplant the brave : </l>
              <l>To the loved banks of Cam, the muses’ seat, </l>
              <l>Of learning and science the retreat, </l>
              <l>Will I retire ; and, blest in my low sphere, </l>
              <l>Leave Vice and Folly still to triumph here.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="corps">Exit</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Now for my senatorial puppets : <stage type="corps">(Goes forward and a circle is
                formed.)</stage>Your servant, gentlemen. — We sat late last night.—</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Winni</speaker>
            <p>Had we carried your Honour’s point, we should not have grudged the hardship of the
              service. You find we are staunch ; not death can affright us : the Sick, the Lame –
              forget their diseases. Poor Mr W—lt—rs came beswaddled up in blankets ; yet all would
              not do : we lost the question.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet H—ce</speaker>
            <p>Ay, that damned W—st—r election has done our business. Three or four thousand pounds,
                <pb n="11" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_11.jpg"/> Well laid out last
              summer, would have done more than three or fourscore thousand can now.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Brother, brother, that is the severest stroke we have felt : such another will compel
              me to quit the stage.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet H—ce</speaker>
            <p>Quit the stage ! What will become of me ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Never fear : I have a way to bring you off safe, as well as myself.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet H—ce</speaker>
            <p>The Devil you have. —I am then one of the happiest dogs in England. What ! No account
              for my American trans..ct.ons ? No enquiry ? No refunding ?</p>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Enter Puppet Y— in a hurry.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Y—</speaker>
            <p>Where, where’s his honour ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Why such in a hurry ? Mr Secretary ? What news from the army ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Y—</speaker>
            <p>There is a desertion on your <foreign xml:lang="fr">corps de reserve</foreign>. The
              Welsh forces have openly revolted ; — but as for the Northern, I can give you no
              certain account of them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>They may try what forage they can get ; but will come back to their colours.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Y—</speaker>
            <p>I have been making fine, smooth, oratorically-affecting speeches to them, and all to
              no purpose : you must hasten into the field of battle yourself, and try if you can
              rally your forces before you are entirely beat out of it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>A most metaphorical description of having lost the M-j-r-ty. Well, Gentlemen, all go
              and do your duty : this is the last public effort we can make. I have some important
              affairs which I must first transact in another place, but I shall meet you at
              Philippi.</p>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Exeunt Punch and his Gang separately</stage>
        </div>
        <div type="3">
          <head type="scene">Scene changes</head>
          <stage type="saut">Enter three puppets in private conference.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Capt[ain] Caledon</speaker>
            <p>Look ye, Gentlemen, I am against your proposal : I will not hear of a screen.</p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="12" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_12.jpg"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mr English</speaker>
            <p>Nor can I approve of your Latitudunarian principles of taking all into play.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mr Worcester</speaker>
            <p>I am against carrying things to extremity. — I hate Punch as much as any of you ; but
              if he will voluntarily go off the stage, then his scene of action ends.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Capt[ain] Caledon</speaker>
            <p>I don’t know that : we have characters which often speak from behind the scenes. In
              short, we do nothing, if, after we have turned him out from being an actor, we make
              him prompter. —The principal characters will get into his blundering way, from the
              blundering cues he will give them.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mr English</speaker>
            <p>Though you may cast yourselves what parts you please ; you may play the General, and
              you the cashier ; yet you know the master cannot bear the name of the old-fashioned,
              high-buskined puppets, which he calls the Tory-Rories.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Capt[ain] Caledon</speaker>
            <p>Without an absolute coalition of all the company, and expelling Punch even from
              behind the scenes, I am determined not to act, but will only come on the stage, as
              Cato did into the theatre, to go out again.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>[Mr] Worcester</speaker>
            <p>The business of the stage must not stand still ; and I would rather play any
              tolerable part, than have it worse performed.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Capt[ain] Caledon</speaker>
            <p>I find Punch has more interest than I imagined, and is pressing a sequel interlude
              behind the scenes, while we are busy on the stage.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mr English&gt;</speaker>
            <p>Which he will call the mock-resignation.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Capt[ain] Caledon</speaker>
            <p>And which will be damned, with every actor in it. —The moment therefore I see the
              rehearsal of it begin, I will leave the company. — You know my sentiments. Adieu.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mr English</speaker>
            <p>This difference of opinion bodes no good. I know not what to think of it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>[Mr] Worcester</speaker>
            <p>I must think of playing the part I have undertaken, as well as I can. And though I
              appear in Punch’s place, I must not talk in the same tone.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mr English</speaker>
            <p>Nor act in the same manner ; unless you would meet with the fate Capt[ain] Caledon
              prognosticated.</p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="13" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_13.jpg"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>[Mr] Worcester</speaker>
            <p>Bless me ! What means this change ? I am no longer free : some secret strings pulls
              back my arm, another moves my tongue ; I am an errant puppet. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Mr English</speaker>
            <p>Something has made a little alteration in me. I don’t move as vigorous as before.
              Someone behind the curtain has got playing tricks with the strings.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>[Mr] Worcester</speaker>
            <p>Hey Day ! Here are half the puppets come on with new motions and new faces.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <stage type="pers">(behind the scenes)</stage>
            <p>Now, Sirs, you shall see what you shall see. — Observe that puppet, that storms and
              raves, and calls names : — with this little touch he is dumb. D’ye see him that stands
              by the scene and won’t come on. — <foreign xml:lang="fr">Presto</foreign> — I dispatch
              this [a]mbassador to him : he takes him by the hand, and he is in action immediately.
              — What’s that fellow talking of war ? — Here, Sir, pull this little string, and he
              turns about : Now, hark —</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>A puppet </speaker>
            <stage type="pers">(squeaks)</stage>
            <p>— Negociations, if honourable, and treaties of N—tr—y may sometimes be allowed. </p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>But Punch, dat vas you dat did squeak de negotiation.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet</speaker>
            <p>But that is not seen by anybody but you, and therefore in the playing this whole
              scene, the joke lies in making them squeak my words in their own voices.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Ver good shoke !</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>But you shall see a better between me and two or three puppets. <stage type="corps"
                >(Goes and confers with puppets at the side of the stage.)</stage>
            </p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Oh ! Dose be mine tr—s—ry puppets —. Vell, and vare be de shole in giving dem pieces
              of sticks ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Why truly that may be no joke to you, but it’s a very good one to me : that very joke
              is worth fifty thousand pounds.</p>
          </sp>
          <pb n="14" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_14.jpg"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>I can’t find it out.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Oh ! That may be ; but I have made many such a joke without your finding it out. —
              Now, Master, you shall make a joke, and that will crown the whole farce.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Ha ! ha ! ha ! Me make joke, Punch ? — Ha ! ha ! ha !</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <stage type="pers">(leading up three puppets)</stage>
            <p>You shall see —. Here is my old friend Will and his wife ; and here is your old
              friend Punch and his daughter.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>And vat den ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Pull that master string and try.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Ha ! ha ! ha ! Good shoke indeed ! — Punch and Will turn to just as Lords, and dere
              wife and shild just as ladies : — Ha ! ha ! How dey strut, and de young wench and de
              old womans flaunt it.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Polly, my dear, you must now remember your rank.</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Pol[ly]</speaker>
            <p>I warrant you, Papa ! —</p>
            <stage type="saut">Song</stage>
            <lg>
              <l>As Lady of Qual, </l>
              <l>I’ll flaunt in the mall, </l>
              <l>While ‘tis said as I trip it along : </l>
              <l>With no title Miss </l>
              <l>A new Lady is </l>
              <l>Old Lords and their Ladies among. </l>
              <l>The people of rep </l>
              <l>Blame Papa’s false step, </l>
              <l>In ennobling the wench of his wh— </l>
              <l>All his power must own, </l>
              <l>For in this he has done </l>
              <l>What was done by no subject before.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>O Pol ! Should a Duke </l>
              <l>Thy lineage rebuke, </l>
              <l>On his own bid him ponder well rather : </l>
              <l>If true what Fame’s told </l>
              <l>Some Nobles — so old — </l>
              <l>A scoundrel have had for a father.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="15" facs="18__GB_PoliticksInMiniature_ENG_BL_15.jpg"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Puppet Will’s Wife</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>O Polly, my dear, </l>
              <l>The titles we’ll bear </l>
              <l>Your Papa and my spouse have got us, </l>
              <l>The honours we claim, </l>
              <l>Though their loss of fame, </l>
              <l>On them lies the censure, and not us.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Punch assembles all the puppets around him.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>You patriots of late, </l>
              <l>Now courtiers so great, </l>
              <l>Of my places you’ve my resignation ; </l>
              <l>Now courtiers, true blue, </l>
              <l>Play your parts to cue, </l>
              <l>What a farce will you show to the nation !</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Grand Chorus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>All courtiers true blue, </l>
              <l>We’ll play to your cue, </l>
              <l>And a farce we will show to the nation.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Curtain drops. Enter before it : Master and Punch. </stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <p>Vell, dis end vid very good shoke, but vat you come now for ?</p>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>O ! Sir, always an epilogue to so grand a performance is expected, and I am come to
              speak it in form.</p>
          </sp>
        </div>
        <div type="5">
          <head type="div5">Epilogue</head>
          <lg>
            <l>Good people all, strange things we do </l>
            <l>In this our burlesque puppet-show : </l>
            <l>But strange as they appear to you, </l>
            <l>They are not stranger than they’re true. </l>
            <l>Some critics of deep penetration, </l>
            <l>May damn our mimic resignation, </l>
            <l>And say that our catastrophe </l>
            <l>Does not with puppet rules agree : </l>
            <l>Vengeance, for Punch’s crimes should catch him, </l>
            <l>And at the last the Devil fetch him. </l>
            <l>We have not brought this scene to view, </l>
            <l>But yet the Devil may have his due.</l>
          </lg>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
