<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="style_xml.css" type="text/css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title
          ref="https://puppetplays.eu/en/oeuvres/255580/venus-and-adonis-or-the-triumphs-of-love"
          >Venus and Adonis; or, the Triumphs of Love.</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="MSK">Maxine Schoehuys-Kreiss</name>
          <resp ref="maxine.schoehuys-kreiss@univ-montp3.fr">Edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="CD">Cécile Decaix</name>
          <resp ref="CD">Transcription and edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="PM">Pierre Massinon</name>
          <resp ref="PM">Transcription and encoding</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <principal ref="didier.plassard@univ-montp3.fr" xml:id="DP">Didier Plassard</principal>
        <sponsor>PuppetPlays project (ERC GA 835193)</sponsor>
        <funder>European Research Council - ERC</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>All Souls College Library - Oxford</distributor>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence>Public domain</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="DOI"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Love conquers all</note>
        <note>Venus and Adonis; or, The Triumphs of Love (1713) is a mock opera that brings together
          Punch and gods from classical mythology. It is the only printed play by Irish puppeteer
          Martin Powell, who met with brief but dazzling success in England at the beginning of the
          18th century. He mostly played in Convent Garden in London, but he also staged plays in
          Bath, Oxford and Bristol. Although Powell sometimes performed plays inspired by English
          legends or ballads sold by book peddlers, he also wrote original texts – one of which
          being Venus and Adonis. Powell’s preface suggests that he worked with Italian machinists.
          It would also seem that two characters (Jupiter and Proserpina) were played by trained
          monkeys.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <personGrp role="audience">
            <p>Not specified</p>
          </personGrp>
        </listPerson>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>All Souls College Library</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <p>Number of pages in the original document: 16</p>
                <p>Number of acts in the original document: 4</p>
                <p>Format of the original document: Printed</p>
              </objectDesc>
            </physDesc>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
        <bibl>
          <title type="main">Venus and Adonis; or, the Triumphs of Love.</title>
          <date>1713</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords source="animationTechniques">
          <term
            source="https://puppetplays.eu/en/techniques-d-animation/1217/marionnette-à-tringle-et-fils"
            >Rod and string marionette</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="literaryTones">
          <term>Comical</term>
          <term>Burlesque</term>
          <term>Parodistic</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="theatricalTechniques">
          <term>Sung play</term>
          <term>Hunting scene</term>
          <term>Ascent to heaven</term>
          <term>Set that comes to life</term>
          <term>Magic spell</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="genre">
          <term>Mock opera</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="keywords">
          <term>Love</term>
          <term>Death</term>
          <term>Hunting</term>
          <term>Latin Mythology</term>
          <term>Metamorphosis</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>The semi-diplomatic norms applied are intended to guide and facilitate the reading of
            the original texts. The transcriptions therefore include spelling and grammatical
            corrections according to current standards.</p>
          <p>The author's orthographic and grammatical corrections have been integrated into the
            text without being marked. Cuts for performance purposes have not been adopted in the
            transcription.</p>
          <p>Syntax has been modernised where it is naturally incorrect or has become
            incomprehensible today. Additions are limited and indicated by square brackets.</p>
          <p>The copyist's obvious errors (scene numbers, character attributions, etc.) have been
            corrected. The list of characters could also be corrected.</p>
        </normalization>
        <punctuation marks="some">
          <p>Punctuation has been corrected according to modern rules.</p>
        </punctuation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text collected during the PuppetPlays project funded by European Union (Grant Agreement
          835193) under Horizon 2020. The PuppetPlays project aims to re-evaluate the contribution
          of the puppets repertoire to the construction of European cultural identity. Its main
          goals is to collect a corpus of representative plays from Western Europe (Germany,
          Austria, Belgium, Spain, France, Great Britain, Italy, Netherlands, Portugal, Switzerland)
          between the 17th and the 21th century. It also tries to identify the characteristics of
          puppet dramaturgy and their variations depending on eras, cultural spheres, producing
          conditions, and the aimed public.</p>
        <p>This edition is the result of university research work, reviewed by the principal
          investigator.</p>
        <p>This transcription and the editorial work are distributed under the <ref
            target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"> Creative Commons
            Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA) </ref> licence.
          This license enables reusers to distribute, remix, adapt, and build upon the material in
          any medium or format for non-commercial purposes only, and only so long as attribution is
          given to the creator. If you remix, adapt, or build upon the material, you must license
          the modified material under identical terms. </p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when-iso="2024-02-14" who="#CD">Transcription and first encoding</change>
      <change when-iso="2024-07-01" who="#PM">Encoding correction</change>
      <change when-iso="2025-03-25" who="#MSK">TEI Header created from a JSON extraction of the
        PuppetPlays' database.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb n="03" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_03.JPG"/>
      <docAuthor>
        <persName>Martin Powell</persName>
      </docAuthor>
      <docTitle>
        <titlePart type="main">A Mock Opera, Called Venus and Adonis; or, The Triumphs of
          Love.</titlePart>
      </docTitle>
      <docEdition>Martin Powell, Venus and Adonis; or, the Triumphs of Love. London: G.
        Parker</docEdition>
      <docDate>1713</docDate>
      <!-- <docEdition>
                    As it is acted at Punch’s Theatre, Covent Garden. Written by Martin Powell.
                        London: Printed by G. Parker, for the Author, and sold at the office of the
                        Theatre, in the Little Piazza, Covent Garden. 1713. (Price 6d.).
                </docEdition>
                
                Cast list exceptionnaly transcribed later in the book, to follow the original's structure. -->
    </front>
    <body>
      <pb n="05" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_05.JPG"/>
      <div type="1">
        <head type="nameA">To the most ingenious Machionists of the Hay-market Theatre</head>
        <p>Sirs,Epistles and prefaces have been so much in fashion of late, that very few plays or
          operas have been published without. Some have been wholly for prose, others for verse;
          some for serious </p>
        <pb n="06" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_06.JPG"/>
        <p>language, other for farce; but all agree in this, that plays are but diversions in what
          kind soever understood. Now left I should appear ignorant of the fashion, and thought
          uncapable of following it, I am obliged to say something too; but since I am resolved
          against any long-learned discourse, I shall only give you a taste of my experience, which
          I hope may be pleasant and diverting.</p>
        <p> You have done me the honour in giving me a sight of your incomparable fancy in
          machinery, I have ever since made it my chiefest thoughts to find out some way whereby</p>
        <pb n="07" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_07.JPG"/>
        <p>I might manifest my desire of expressing my obligation, which I cannot do in a more
          publi[c] manner than thus. The end of this address is, that I am in great hopes this
          little opera will gain a greater reputation, it being patronized by you, whose genius is
          so great and brains so fertile, that certainly the opera of France and Italy must drop
          whilst you absent yourselves from thence to instruct the stage of Great-Britain. Such
          projectors as you give new life to invention; your foreign pencil likewise instructs
          painters. Indeed, the latter two are akin, being the effects of fancy, and one </p>

        <pb n="08" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_08.JPG"/>

        <p> oftentimes helps out the other, as may be seen in your last great and rich machine. </p>
        <p>All must own, that it was most ingenious, surprising, and uncommon, particularly the vast
          number of curling clouds, like a mighty sea, it brought before it; and as it gently moved
          towards the spectators, it appeared more wonderful to see those raref[ied] clouds striving
          to outvie each other in brightness; their quick contraction, and sudd[en] forming
          themselves to a temple. For my part, I was astonished at the sight, and fanc[ied] myself
          to be in some c[e]lestial sphere. Oh! that</p>
        <pb n="09" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_09.JPG"/>
        <p> my little inventions were not confined like a butterfly in a tar-barrel, and had a stage
          in circumference containing an acre, yet not one of my wooden-headed managers would be
          capable of bringing so great a machine to such perfection, which I dare not so much as
          imitate. My callow-winged fancy dare not soar so high, lest it should be compared with the
          foolish arcades, that presumed, that if they could once attain to the top of a certain
          mountain they might reach the moon; but when they, with a great deal of pains, had reached
          the top of it, how much they fell short of their aim is easy</p>
        <pb n="10" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_10.JPG"/>
        <p> to guess. So least my aspiring thoughts should make me share the same fate, I’ll end
          this epistle, strengthened with the hopes, that when you have seen this little
          performance, you’ll do me the honour of recommending it to your friends abroad, and you
          will highly oblige, </p>
        <p>Your most obedient Humble servant, M. Powell.</p>
      </div>
      <pb n="11" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_11.JPG"/>
      <div type="1">
        <head type="nameA">The Preface to the Reader</head>
        <p>That which induced me to print this little opera was in my great patron, Punch, who,
          meeting with some reflections from the greater opera, comparing his little fabric to a
          tar-barre[l], and his person to a butterfly, which highly displeased him, and to vent his
          spleen beat his empty noddle against every scene.</p> <pb n="12"
            facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_12.JPG"/> <p> And all the little gentry seemed to
          resent the same, and discovered their chagr[in] by nodding their wooden heads at each
          other; nor could their fury be appeased, till King Bladud, and Whittington, promised to
          supply them with a large sum of money, to enable them to erect an opera, which could not
          be contained in a tar-barrel, and so the rupture ceased.</p>
      </div>
      <pb n="13" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_13.JPG"/>
      <div type="2">
        <head type="nameT">Prologue</head>
        <lg>
          <l>As the industrious bee, in verdant meads, </l>
          <l>Oft draws mellifluous juice from rankest weeds; </l>
          <l>So I, from urns of lovers long since slain, </l>
          <l>Produce most noble acts, and spare no pain, </l>
          <l>Nor cost, if I to please you may attain. </l>
          <l>Venus and Adonis, of beauty bright, </l>
          <l>I humbly offer to your piercing sight. </l>
          <l>No loose expression here shall pass for wit, </l>
          <l>No blasphemy affright, the trembling pit: </l>
          <l>No modish curse, shall lard a trifling scene, </l>
          <l>Nor roaring hero, swear and nothing mean. <pb n="14"
              facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_14.JPG"/>
          </l>
          <l>To choose diversions, such shall be my care, </l>
          <l>As shall not give offence to any virtuous ear; </l>
          <l>Such as shall give to everyone delight, </l>
          <l>Such as you’ll see presented here tonight, </l>
          <l>Will give offence to neither church nor state, </l>
          <l>Burlesque no text, buffoon no magistrate; </l>
          <l>Laugh at no law, but with such caution move, </l>
          <l>As will, if possible, deserve your love. </l>
          <l>No longer shall poor Punch in fetters toil, </l>
          <l>Nor with complaints his tedious hours beguile, </l>
          <l>Whilst you thus shine upon him with a smile; </l>
          <l>He still for blessing on you all shall pray, </l>
          <l>And tributary thanks shall thus forever pay.</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <pb n="15" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_15.JPG"/>
      
      <castList>
        <head type="personnage">Dramatis Personae</head>
       
          <head type="personnage">Men</head>
          <castItem>
            <role>Adonis</role>
            <roleDesc>A little smooth-faced youth finely dressed, adorned with the best spangles and
              gold-tabby that came last from Italy, and never seen on the stage before.</roleDesc>
          </castItem>
          <castItem>
            <role>Cupid</role>
            <roleDesc>A trifle; a very great mischief-maker; one who makes old men children, and
              boys set up for men; newly arrived from the hands of the workman.</roleDesc>
          </castItem>
          <castItem>
            <role>Jupiter</role>
            <roleDesc>That by his mock rattling breaks all things to pieces. Performed by a
              mischievous ape.</roleDesc>
          </castItem>
          <castItem>
            <role>Mars</role>
            <roleDesc>Your old friend Punch, who from a coxcombly shepherd is transformed by Jupiter
              to the mock god of battle, and bantered with the love or Proserpine.</roleDesc>
            
          </castItem>      
      </castList>
      
      <castList> 
      <head type="personnage">Women</head> 
          <castItem>
           
            <role>Venus</role>
            <roleDesc>A devilish goddess that has ruined millions of people, and never was so sorry
              till her loved Adonis was killed, dressed like the fair deceivers that imitate
              her.</roleDesc>
          </castItem>
          <castItem>
            <role>Pallas</role>
            <roleDesc>The reverse of Minerva, looks like an alderman with a grave face, and little
              wisdom, who sings much, and consequently requires little wit.</roleDesc>
          </castItem>
          <castItem>
            <role>Proserpine</role>
            <roleDesc>Whom Punch runs mad for; performed by a monkey lately dead, who sings as well
              as if she had been living.</roleDesc>
          </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Pan, satyrs, nymphs, and swains.</role>
        </castItem>
      </castList>
      <pb n="17" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_17.JPG"/>
      <div type="1">
        <head type="nameA">Venus and Adonis: or, the triumphs of Love.</head>
        <head type="acte" n="1">Act I</head>
        <div type="3">
          <head type="scene" n="1">Scene 1</head>
          <head type="nameS">Cupid’s Bower.</head>
          <stage type="saut">Enter Cupid, meeting Venus.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Cupid</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Welcome, love’s goddess, and royal mother: </l>
              <l>What brought bright Venus here to Cupid’s bower? </l>
              <l>How came that lovely face with grief oppress[sed]? </l>
              <l>Can Cupid give his beauteous mother rest?</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Venus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Cupid, my son, whose uncontr[ol]ling sway </l>
              <l>Makes all c[e]lestial deities obey. </l>
              <l>O force Adonis’ heart to yield to love, </l>
              <l>Of all thy works, the master-piece ’twill prove. </l>
              <l>O, kindle flames in him, like those in me, </l>
              <l>And grant, that I his beauty soon may see. <pb n="18"
                  facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_18.JPG"/>
              </l>
              <l>Let me then view those eyes, whose shining light, </l>
              <l>Alone can pleasure give to Venus’ sight. </l>
              <l>Just like a ship, whilst every mountain-wave </l>
              <l>Threatens the ma[r]iners with a gaping grave; </l>
              <l>Such is my case, and so my state appears, </l>
              <l>Alike distracted, between hopes and fears. </l>
              <l>Into the woods I’ll go, and there complain, </l>
              <l>Nor think of pleasure, till you come again.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Cupid</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Despair not, mother, Adonis shall be thine, </l>
              <l>Or never let Cupid in your favour shine. </l>
              <l>From yonder mount, that overlooks. My bower, </l>
              <l>Adonis now descends; ‘tis Venus happy hour. </l>
              <l>With my keen dart, I will so pierce his breast, </l>
              <l>That none but your soft arms, shall give him rest.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Exeunt</stage>
        </div>
        <div type="3">
          <head type="scene" n="2">Scene 2</head>
          <head type="nameS">A forest</head>
          <stage type="saut">Enter Punch in a shepherd’s habit.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>Was ever mortal so affronted? To be scorned by all the nymphs, and denied to hunt
              with the swains? God Pan too, with his cloven-footed gang of satyrs to mock me.
              [G]ad’s bobs, now I’m in the humour to abuse [th]em all. Jupiter is a juggler, Mars is
              a bully, Apollo a poor paultry poet, Bacchus a drunken drawer, Mercury a
              morris-dancing pimp, Venus a town-jilt, Cupid a blind archer, and Pan a savage
              cuckold.</p>
            <lg>
              <l>And I’m resolved, if I meet [th]em in the chase,</l>
              <l>I’ll throw my doubled fist in their face.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Exit</stage>
          <pb n="19" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_19.JPG"/>
          <stage type="saut">Enter Cupid</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Cupid</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>And scorns the power, </l>
              <l>That all the gods adore? </l>
              <l>He that dare slight the beloved muses’ sound, </l>
              <l>With my keen arrow, shall receive his wound. </l>
              <l>I’ll curse thee with loving Proserpine.</l>
              <stage type="saut">Throws an arrow.</stage>
              <l>With my swift wings I’ll take my speedy flight, </l>
              <l> Lest young Adonis should escape my sight.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Ascends</stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <pb n="20" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_20.JPG"/>
      <div type="1">
        <head type="acte" n="2">Act II</head>
        <div type="3">
          <head type="scene" n="1">Scene I</head>
          <stage type="saut">First stage a village</stage>
          <stage type="saut">Enter Punch</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Punch</speaker>
            <p>I will justify, that a man had better have the Devil ride through his guts with a
              bundle of thorns at his bre[e]ch, than to be in love; and as the Devil would have it,
              with Proserpine. Sure I was in a woundy heat when I went to hell to choose a mistress:
              it was the other day that I was railing against love and poetry; and now I think of
              nothing else, and eat nothing but poetry, and now it wombles to come forth. See, she
              comes.</p>
            <stage type="saut">Proserpine rises in a cave</stage>
            <lg>
              <l>Proserpine, thou whose beauty doth enrich us, </l>
              <l>Tell me the cause, why thou dost so bewitch us: </l>
              <l>This day my love was born, though not begotten, </l>
              <l>This day I’ll think on, when I’m dead and rotten. </l>
              <l>And though thy coyness, and thy pretty scorn, </l>
              <l>Makes many wish, that thou ha[d] never been born; </l>
              <l>Yet for my part, this I will swear and say, </l>
              <l>I wish thy time of birth were every day. </l>
              <l>So Venus looked, when the Idalian boy </l>
              <l>Confirmed her beauty, with the curse of Troy; </l>
              <l>Just so she looked, with such an air she smiled, </l>
              <l>When she two rival goddesses beguiled. </l>
              <l>Thy double tire of teeth do show, forsooth, </l>
              <l>Whiter than ivory, or a bitch’s tooth, <pb n="21"
                  facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_21.JPG"/>
              </l>
              <l>Thy voice like bird in hedge, in time of Spring, </l>
              <l>Do[e]s bewitch me confoundedly to sing.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage type="saut">The song</stage>
            <lg>
              <l>Proserpine, ’tis to thee I sing, </l>
              <l>I love thee more than anything. </l>
              <l>Love and fire’s got in my head, </l>
              <l>Then take me quickly to thy bed, </l>
              <l>But what to do need not be said. </l>
              <l>With a ho, with a ha, </l>
              <l>With a ho, ho, ho, etc. </l>
              <l>Love and fire’s got, etc.</l>
            </lg>
            <stage type="saut">Proserpine sinks</stage>
            <lg>
              <l>She’s gone! She’s sunk! She’s dead! She’s buried! </l>
              <l>I shall go mad, I’ll roar, and rant, and swear; </l>
              <l>And all this I will do, because I dare. </l>
              <l>Since she’s dead, what method shall I take </l>
              <l>To raise some monument that’s wondrous great? </l>
              <l>To enrich her tomb, nor shrines, mor altars spare, </l>
              <l>But strip the shining gods to make it rare.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="22" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_22.JPG"/>
          </sp>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="1">
        <head type="acte" n="3">Act III</head>
        <div type="3">
          <head type="scene" n="1">Scene 1</head>
          <stage type="saut">The palace of Venus, adorned with proper ornaments, and the statues of
            the Pantheon heightened with gold.</stage>
          <stage type="saut">Enter Venus and Adonis.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Venus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Let music sound from the c[e]lestial sphere, </l>
              <l>Whilst satyrs, swains, and nymphs, divert us here. </l>
              <l>Let mortal join the deities above, </l>
              <l>To crown the triumphs of my glorious love.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Shepherds, shepherdesses and satyrs, dance. </stage>
          <stage type="saut">The horn sounds.</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Adonis</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Hark! Diana’s horn invites me to the chase: </l>
              <l>The gods in full divan have all decreed, </l>
              <l>That a most monstrous boar this day shall bleed.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Venus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Adonis, wil[l] thou then from me be gone, </l>
              <l>And leave me he[re] to mourn and sigh alone? </l>
              <l>Regar[d] thou not the flower of my youth, </l>
              <l>When of my love, thou ha[s] so large a proof? </l>
              <l>Thou captivated ha[s] long since my hear, </l>
              <l>And wil[l] thou now unkindly from me part? </l>
              <l>O, do not go, the danger’s very great; </l>
              <l>Thy death, I much do fear, it will create.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <pb n="23" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_23.JPG"/>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Adonis</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Let my fair goddess, from sad grief forbear, </l>
              <l>For no danger in these huntings are; </l>
              <l>Let Venus then, banish al thoughts of fear. </l>
              <l>He that from beauty’s charms too long doth rove, </l>
              <l>Never yet knew the sweets of youthful love.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Exeunt</stage>
        </div>
        <div type="3">
          <head type="scene" n="2">Scene 2</head>
          <stage type="saut">A forest</stage>
          <stage type="saut">The Horn sounds, the wild boar crosses the stage; and after him God
            Pan, Adonis, Swains, and Satyrs in chase. Re-enter Adonis, wounded. </stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Adonis</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>Ah, what a sad unfortunate Man was I, </l>
              <l>Not to observe the tears of her fair eye: </l>
              <l>Her sweet persuasions were, I should not go; </l>
              <l>Still to her suit I ever answered, no. </l>
              <l>And yet grim Death, it is not thee I fear, </l>
              <l>For her alone is all my grief and care. </l>
              <l>Adieu, fair Venus, adieu to thee a while, </l>
              <l>Our future joys will make us both to smile.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Dies.</stage>
          <stage type="saut">Enter Venus, and kneels</stage>
          <sp>
            <speaker>Venus</speaker>
            <lg>
              <l>What cruel fate brought this sight hither? </l>
              <l>Why did we not die both together? </l>
              <l>How sad and unhappy is Venus’ fate, </l>
              <l>Thus to be made at once unfortunate? </l>
              <l>He’s gone! He’s gone! The glorious youth is fled: </l>
              <l>Then why do I in vain bewail the dead? <pb n="24"
                  facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_24.JPG"/>
              </l>
              <l>My doves and chariot, now with speed prepare, </l>
              <l>His Soul I’ll overtake, though flying through the air; </l>
              <l>The deities above, I then will move, </l>
              <l>For life eternal to my god-like love.</l>
            </lg>
          </sp>
          <stage type="saut">Exit</stage>
          <stage type="saut">Curtain drops</stage>
        </div>
      </div>
      <pb n="25" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_25.JPG"/>
      <div type="1">
        <head type="acte" n="4">Act IV</head>
        <stage type="saut">Soft musi[c] as the machines descend. After the first machine, Venus and
          Pallas descend in two several machines; at the feet of Venus two dogs, and at Pallas’ an
          owl and a cock. The two lesser machines break through the larger, and move to the front of
          the stage. </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Venus</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Let great Apollo now the muses join, </l>
            <l>Whi[le] I, in tears, do mourn the youth divine: </l>
            <l>For all my earthly joys at once are fled, </l>
            <l>My beloved Adonis being dead.</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Pallas</speaker>
          <stage type="saut"> sings</stage>
          <lg>
            <l>If now the smiles of Pallas ought you prize, </l>
            <l>My dearest Venus, dry up thy watery eyes: </l>
            <l>The gods all mourn throughout their spheres </l>
            <l>To see love’s Goddess drowned in tears. <pb n="26"
                facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_26.JPG"/>
            </l>
            <l>Drowned in tears, </l>
            <l>Drowned in tears, </l>
            <l>To see love’s Goddess drowned in tears.</l>
          </lg>
          <stage type="saut">They ascend.</stage>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">Jupiter and Proserpine descend in the front of the stage, and sing;
          whilst Mars descends in his palace, and moves towards them.</stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Jupiter</speaker>
          <stage type="saut">sings</stage>
          <lg>
            <l>O Proserpine, look up and see </l>
            <l>Great Jove descend to visit thee; </l>
            <l>Likewise Punch, by thee so hated, </l>
            <l>To great Mars is now translated: </l>
            <l>Then take the God into thy arms, </l>
            <l>Lest thundering Jove, should crush thy charms, </l>
            <l>Crush thy charms, </l>
            <l>Crush thy charms, </l>
            <l>Lest thundering Jove, should crush thy charms, </l>
            <l>Crush thy charms, </l>
            <l>Crush thy charms, </l>
            <l>Lest thundering Jove, should crush thy charms.</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb n="27" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_27.JPG"/>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Proserpine</speaker>
          <stage type="saut">sings</stage>
          <lg>
            <l>The commands of love I’ll obey, </l>
            <l>Love is dangerous to delay, </l>
            <l>Since Punch has stolen my heart away. </l>
            <l>Let Pluto rave, and tear his brain, </l>
            <l>’Tis Mars, or Punch, must quench my flame, </l>
            <l>Quench my flame, </l>
            <l>Quench my flame, </l>
            <l>’Tis Mars, or Punch, must quench my flame.</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <pb n="28" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_28.JPG"/>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mars</speaker>
          <stage type="saut">sings</stage>
          <lg>
            <l>Then take great Mars into thy arms </l>
            <l>And thou shalt rifle all my charms: </l>
            <l>In wanton love whole nights we’ll range, </l>
            <l>And now and then a haugh we’ll change. </l>
            <l>Let’s now ascend with Jove above, </l>
            <l>And with our haugh proclaim our love, </l>
            <l>With a ha, ha, ha, ha, proclaim our love.</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">They all ascend.</stage>
      </div>
      <pb n="29" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_29.JPG"/>
      <div type="5">
        <head type="div5">Iris descends on a rainbow, and speaks the epilogue</head>
        <lg>
          <l>Swift! Swifter still! For methinks I move to[o] slow. </l>
          <l>What holds my silver wings from making haste, </l>
          <l>When every cloud I see sails by so fast? </l>
          <l>Luna flies wrapped in foggy clouds of night, </l>
          <l>To shun the rays of bright Apollo’s light. </l>
          <l>See with what haste the feathered hours run, </l>
          <l>To dress the gaudy chariot of the sun: <pb n="30"
              facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_30.JPG"/>
          </l>
          <l>Whilst nymphs and swains, at love’s bright alter meet, </l>
          <l>Their sacred vows to pay at Venus’ feet. </l>
          <l>For till old time his c[ry]st[a]l glass hath hurled, </l>
          <l>And from it lost the ashes of the world, </l>
          <l>No mortal shall be free from Cupid’s dart, </l>
          <l>But love shall triumph over every heart.</l>
        </lg>
        <pb n="31" facs="18_GB_POWELL_VenusAndAdonis_ENG_SOLO_31.JPG"/>
        <stage type="saut">As Iris ascends, the clouds break, and discover the British machin[e]ry,
          beautified with the figure of her Britanni[c] majesty, seated on her throne, attended by
          the honourable House of Peers, and Chief Ministers of State. </stage>
        <stage type="saut">The Machines break into several triumphant arches, and form themselves
          into double and treble prospects, with all the trophies taken from the enemy under their
          feet. </stage>
      </div>
      <div type="5">
        <head type="div5">Finis</head>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
