<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="style_xml.css" type="text/css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title ref="https://puppetplays.eu/en/oeuvres/239073/burlesque-upon-magistracy-or-punch-out-of-humour">Burlesque upon Magistracy; or, Punch out of Humour</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="MSK">Maxine Schoehuys-Kreiss</name>
          <resp ref="maxine.schoehuys-kreiss@univ-montp3.fr">Edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="CD">Cécile Decaix</name>
          <resp ref="">Transcription and edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="PM">Pierre Massinon</name>
          <resp ref="stagiaire">Transcription and encoding</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <principal ref="didier.plassard@univ-montp3.fr" xml:id="DP">Didier Plassard</principal>
        <sponsor>PuppetPlays project (ERC GA 835193)</sponsor>
        <funder>European Research Council - ERC</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Royal Irish Academy - Dublin, Ireland</distributor>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence>Public domain</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="DOI"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>A thief disguises himself as a magistrate</note>
        <note>Burlesque upon Magistracy; or, Punch out of
                    Humour is a play printed in London and in Dublin in
                    1736. The title page indicates that the show can be seen at the
                    “Roiting House" of a certain Don Parabocka, but that its script is printed because
                    it is entirely new and an "intelligent interpreter" has not yet been
                    found.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <personGrp role="audience">
            <p>Not specified</p>
          </personGrp>
          
        </listPerson>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>Royal Irish Academy</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <p>Number of pages in the original document: 8</p>
                <p>Number of acts in the original document: 1</p>
                <p>Format of the original document: Printed</p>
              </objectDesc>
            </physDesc>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
        <bibl>
          <title type="main">Burlesque upon Magistracy; or, Punch out of Humour</title>
          <date>1736</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords source="animationTechniques">
          <term source="https://puppetplays.eu/en/techniques-d-animation/1217/marionnette-à-tringle-et-fils">Rod and string marionette</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="literaryTones">
          <term/>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="theatricalTechniques">
          <term>Arrest scene</term>
          <term>Court scene</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="genre">
          <term>Farce</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="keywords">
          <term>Revenge</term>
          <term>Judgment</term>
          <term>Thief</term>
          <term>Morality</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>The semi-diplomatic norms applied are intended to guide and facilitate the reading of the original texts. The transcriptions therefore include spelling and grammatical corrections according to current standards.</p>
          <p>The author's orthographic and grammatical corrections have been integrated into the text without being marked. Cuts for performance purposes have not been adopted in the transcription.</p>
          <p>Syntax has been modernised where it is naturally incorrect or has become incomprehensible today. Additions are limited and indicated by square brackets.</p>
          <p>The copyist's obvious errors (scene numbers, character attributions, etc.) have been corrected. The list of characters could also be corrected.</p>
        </normalization>
        <punctuation marks="some">
          <p>Punctuation has been corrected according to modern rules.</p>
        </punctuation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text collected during the PuppetPlays project funded by European Union (Grant
        Agreement 835193) under Horizon 2020. The PuppetPlays project aims to
        re-evaluate the contribution of the puppets repertoire to the construction of
        European cultural identity. Its main goals is to collect a corpus of
        representative plays from Western Europe (Germany, Austria, Belgium, Spain,
        France, Great Britain, Italy, Netherlands, Portugal, Switzerland) between the
        17th and the 21th century. It also tries to identify the characteristics of
        puppet dramaturgy and their variations depending on eras, cultural spheres,
        producing conditions, and the aimed public.</p>
        <p>This edition is the result of university research work, reviewed by the principal
        investigator.</p>
        <p>This transcription and the editorial work are distributed under the <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"> Creative
            Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA)
        </ref> licence. This license enables reusers to distribute, remix, adapt, and
        build upon the material in any medium or format for non-commercial purposes
        only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator. If you remix,
        adapt, or build upon the material, you must license the modified material under
        identical terms. </p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when-iso="2024-01-09" who="#CD">Transcription and first encoding</change>
      <change when-iso="2024-07-01" who="#PM">Encoding correction</change>
      <change when-iso="2025-03-24" who="#MSK">TEI Header created from a JSON extraction of the PuppetPlays' database.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb n="1" facs="18_IRL__BurlesqueUponMagistracy_ENG_RIA_01.png"/>
      <!-- <docEdition>
                This is to give notice to all Gentlemen,
                    Ladies and others, that there is to be seen
                    at the roiting house of the late famous Don Parabocka; a new and
                    diverting Puppet Show, called The
            </docEdition> -->
      <docTitle>
        <titlePart type="main">Burlesque upon magistracy; or, Punch out of humour</titlePart>
      </docTitle>
      <docEdition>Dublin
          </docEdition>
      <docDate>1736</docDate>
      <!--  <docEdition>As this farce is entirely new, and we have not been able to procure an intelligent interpreter; it is humbly hoped, that this
                method of dispersing copies of the representation will not be prejudicial to us
                when it comes to appear upon the stage.
            </docEdition> -->
      <castList>
        <head type="personnage">The Chief Puppets are</head>
        <castItem>
          <role>Gormoncho</role>
          <roleDesc>The Mock Magistrate</roleDesc>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Punch</role>
          <roleDesc>His Son</roleDesc>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Wyario</role>
          <roleDesc>His Clerk</roleDesc>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Mopsa</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>The Magistrate's Daughter</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Burghers</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Common-Council-Men</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Constables</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Serjeants</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>And other Attendants, as at a Sessions</role>
        </castItem>
      </castList>
      <pb n="2" facs="18_IRL__BurlesqueUponMagistracy_ENG_RIA_02.png"/>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="1">
        <head type="nameA">This is to give notice to all Gentlemen, Ladies and others, etc
                </head>
        <stage type="saut">The first figure we present you is Punch, who 
                    seems to be in a great fury at some insult he 
                    heard had been offered to his sister, Mopsa.
                </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Punch</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>By all the Gods, I’ll fret my guts,
                         </l>
            <l>To fiddle strings – I’ve learnt my struts –
                         </l>
            <l>My honour cannot bear such usage,
                         </l>
            <l>Since Father now is on a new stage;
                         </l>
            <l>Now sage Gormoncho rules the city,
                         </l>
            <l>Now sister Mopsa’s grown so pretty;
                         </l>
            <l>I’ll teach those riotous defamers,
                         </l>
            <l>Of what respect we now are claimers;
                         </l>
            <l>I’ll vengence have, confound me, will I,
                         </l>
            <l>Must Punch be thought for ever silly?
                        </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">Gentlemen and Ladies pray take notice, the next
                            figure we present you is the beautiful Mopsa,
                            encouraging her brother Punch to hasten his
                            revenge.
                        </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mopsa</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Dear Brother, by your ties of duty,
                       </l>
            <l>Redress the wrong that’s done my beauty;
                           
                  </l>
            <pb n="3" facs="18_IRL__BurlesqueUponMagistracy_ENG_RIA_03.png"/>
            <l>Was ever tender maid so hurted,
                       </l>
            <l>By one whom I so often have courted?
                       </l>
            <l>Whom I – (but may my curses catch him)
                       </l>
            <l>Oh, haste, dear Fatty, to dispatch him –
                       </l>
            <l>My injuries I’ve often repeated,
                       </l>
            <l>Wants still your courage to be whetted?
                       </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Punch</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Mopsa, I own I’m flow of thinking,
                    </l>
            <l>Oft’ are my senses fog’d by drinking;
                    </l>
            <l>Nor is my courage of the quickest,
                    </l>
            <l>Unless a tender point thou prickest.
                    </l>
            <l>But now, as you were just appearing,
                    </l>
            <l>I have been swaggering, storming, swearing;
                    </l>
            <l>No boyling water is more frothy,
                    </l>
            <l>No Captain Bluff was half so wrothy;
                    </l>
            <l>When quick – strange chilliness of blood!
                    </l>
            <l>Confounded at your sight I stood ---
                    </l>
            <l>I shook more fast than leaf of aspin,
                    </l>
            <l>My throat I thought Alanio grasping;
                    </l>
            <l>No culverin discharged was quieter,
                    </l>
            <l>I fancy ev’ry bush a rioter ---
                    </l>
            <l>My fears are now again defeated,
                    </l>
            <l>Repeat your wrongs, to keep me heated.
                    </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mopsa</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>No – dastardly misshapen Elfe,
                    </l>
            <l>I’ll execute my rage myself –
                    </l>
            <l>To old Gormoncho I’ll complain,
                    </l>
            <l>Papa don’t bear the rod in vain;
                    </l>
            <l>I know he hates Alanio’s kindred,
                    </l>
            <l>To all his Friends has malice inbred;
                    </l>
            <l>Will punish for his filthy song,
                    </l>
            <l>No matter whether right or wrong.
                        <pb n="4" facs="18_IRL__BurlesqueUponMagistracy_ENG_RIA_04.png"/>
                  </l>
            <l>But see – he makes his publick entry –
                    </l>
            <l>What crowds of corporation gentry!
                    </l>
            <l>See how he struts it in regalia –
                    </l>
            <l>So oft’ I’ve seen of Ham Westfalia;
                    </l>
            <l>Fat slices graced with leaves of laurel,
                    </l>
            <l>Or ill-sav’d God in clean hoop’d Barrel – 
                    </l>
            <l>But what care I, how much uncomely,
                    </l>
            <l>He looks – so I my Vengeance come by –
                    </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">The next figure we present you is the sage
                    Gormoncho, with a white wand in his hand,
                    Not unlike a mayor’s rod, he should have made
                    His appearance in the regalia that his daughter
                    Mopsa fancies him drest in, but as we
                    were coming to this town, a vagabond fellow,
                    who had once been Sub-Sheriff of the county
                    G ---, and was obliged to fly for malpractices,
                    met us on the road, and robbed us of 
                    them all.
                </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Gormoncho</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Call in Wyario – fix my cushion,
                    </l>
            <l>See that no bold insulters rush on – 
                    </l>
            <l>In silence let the mob adore us,
                    </l>
            <l>Let all complainants come before us –
                    </l>
            <l>But first Wyario, read the indictment,
                    </l>
            <l>For our regalia that by slight went --
                    </l>
            <l>For tho delinquent’s <stage type="corps">non inventus</stage>,
                    </l>
            <l>To find the bill that shan’t prevent us;
                    </l>
            <l>I can the vagrant paint minutely;
                    </l>
            <l>His birth and life know most acutely – 
                        <pb n="5" facs="18_IRL__BurlesqueUponMagistracy_ENG_RIA_05.png"/>
                  </l>
            <l>And, tho’s our daughter has a grievance,
                    </l>
            <l>That wants (she says) our quick relievance;
                    </l>
            <l>Yet since that’s but a private evil,
                    </l>
            <l>To hear a public wrong’s more civil.
                    </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">Here Wyario reads a long accusation against
                    persons unknown, for robbing the Show-Man
                    of his regalia, as also a proclamation with
                    reward to anyone that shall discover the thief,
                    and then concludes as you shall hear.
                </stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Wyario</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Oyes – It is his worship’s pleasure,
                    </l>
            <l>All people hear his tale at leisure.
                    </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Gormoncho</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Good burghers, councilmen and commons,
                      </l>
            <l>Know you, for what I sent my summons;
                      </l>
            <l>I sent – because in public meeting,
                      </l>
            <l>To tell such vilanies is fitting;
                      </l>
            <l>That so by many one’s assistance,
                      </l>
            <l>We’ll nab the rogue tho’ now at distance –
                      </l>
            <l>This wretch (tho’ once I thought him honest
                      </l>
            <l>Often if men our notion’s wrongest)
                      </l>
            <l>From poor but virtuous folk took birth,
                      </l>
            <l>Far westward on our Irish earth.
                      </l>
            <l>His parents held a decent dwelling,
                      </l>
            <l>Fit for their calling, good ale selling,
                      </l>
            <l>This I know well for to this minute,
                      </l>
            <l>They still live there, and draw ale in it –
                      </l>
            <l>Their son (our royal robes purloiner,
                      </l>
            <l>Don’t think I’m of a fiction coiner)
                          <pb n="6" facs="18_IRL__BurlesqueUponMagistracy_ENG_RIA_06.png"/>
                  </l>
            <l>With Sub-Attorney served as [ap]prentice,
                      </l>
            <l>From thence to act as Sheriff sent is;
                      </l>
            <l>The county’s money (strong temptation,
                      </l>
            <l>For such a reptile education)
                      </l>
            <l>Is wisely to his trust committed,
                      </l>
            <l>And he as well the county fitted;
                      </l>
            <l>He humbly owns himself their debtor
                      </l>
            <l>Will reimburse, when times are better;
                      </l>
            <l>But for the present begs excuse,
                      </l>
            <l>He’ll put your money out to use –
                      </l>
            <l>This forced the wretch to skulk among us,
                      </l>
            <l>Waiting for power and time to wrong us –
                      </l>
            <l>His make is of the lower stature,
                      </l>
            <l>Tho’ vile his heart, has smiling feature;
                      </l>
            <l>And when in private has undone you,
                      </l>
            <l>Is most in public fawning on you;
                      </l>
            <l>His paunch rotu[nd] and somewhat gross is,
                      </l>
            <l>Near my own size he pretty close is;
                      </l>
            <l>By this d[e]scription you may guess him,
                      </l>
            <l>Dear friends be zealous, to suppress him,
                      </l>
            <l>Now Mopsa, child, declare, why grieve you,
                      </l>
            <l>Your father’s power shall soon relieve you.</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Mopsa</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Good Sir, were not that Punch a coward,
                   </l>
            <l>More base than is your serjeant H-;
                   </l>
            <l>Your Worship need not now be vext,
                   </l>
            <l>Nor my young heart so long perplex –
                   </l>
            <l>But since he’s frighted – this my Case is – 
                   </l>
            <l>And sure you’ll think it worth redress is –
                       <pb n="7" facs="18_IRL__BurlesqueUponMagistracy_ENG_RIA_07.png"/>
                  </l>
            <l>One night (your Worship then was farming)
                   </l>
            <l>As in my bed I just was warming;
                   </l>
            <l>I heard (don’t bid me sp[ea]ke it plainly)
                   </l>
            <l>I heard Alanio sing obscenely;
                   </l>
            <l>His song I can’t repeat so naught it,
                   </l>
            <l>His voice it was or so I thought it –
                   </l>
            <l>And sure to know that voice was easy,
                   </l>
            <l>That voice had once sole power to please me;
                   </l>
            <l>Surprized at such an odd proceeding,
                   </l>
            <l>I rose to check his want of breeding;
                   </l>
            <l>Perhaps abused him in my passion,
                   </l>
            <l>For full my heart was of vexation;
                   </l>
            <l>To hear him such affronts negotiate,
                   </l>
            <l>With Porabock that vile associate;
                   </l>
            <l>The whole abuse I don’t remember,
                   </l>
            <l>I know he wished me some good member
                   </l>
            <l>(So chast[e] my mind it did not strike it)
                   </l>
            <l>For Sir indeed, I do not like it,
                   </l>
            <l>He comes – Oh punish such offenses,
                   </l>
            <l>His very sight distracts my senses –</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">The figure we present you is Alanio, who comes
                    attented with two constables to arrest
                    Gormoncho, who tho’ arrived to, and concealed
                    under the magistracy, is at last dicovered to be the very rogue that stole the regalia. But 
                    before Alanio has time to sp[ea]ke, Gormoncho
                    bawls out.
                </stage>
        <pb n="8" facs="18_IRL__BurlesqueUponMagistracy_ENG_RIA_08.png"/>
        <sp>
          <!-- No stage direction here. Gormoncho ?  -->
          <lg>
            <l>Sergeants, my friends, secure that vil[l]ain,
                   </l>
            <l>Here you Wyario, bring the bill in;
                   </l>
            <l>That slave shall feel my utmost fury –
                   </l>
            <l>(Since brother burghers are his jury)   <stage type="corps">(Aside)</stage>
                  </l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Alanio</speaker>
          <lg>
            <l>Deluded people read this warrant,
                        <stage type="corps">(Your ruler proves a knave most arrant)</stage>
                  </l>
            <l>From western justices directed –</l>
            <l>His full blown crimes are now detected –</l>
            <l>This is the very rogue you fought for,</l>
            <l>Such a vile wretch who can say ought for</l>
            <l>Your Pris[o]ner, quickly, sergeants, haul away,</l>
            <l>Strip him, and send him back to G -</l>
          </lg>
          <stage type="saut">Exeunt</stage>
          <lg>
            <l>A Moral in our little Shew is
                    </l>
            <l>Nor it’s design so hard to know is.</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
      </div>
      <div type="5">
        <head type="div5">Finis</head>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
