<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="style-xml.css" type="text/css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title ref="https://puppetplays.eu/en/oeuvres/168267/tu-chanteras-tu-ne-chanteras">Tu chanteras, tu ne chanteras</title>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="MSK">Maxine Schoehuys-Kreiss</name>
          <resp ref="maxine.schoehuys-kreiss@univ-montp3.fr">Edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name xml:id="PM">Pierre Massinon</name>
          <resp>Transcription and edition</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <principal ref="didier.plassard@univ-montp3.fr" xml:id="DP">Didier Plassard</principal>
        <sponsor>PuppetPlays project (ERC GA 835193)</sponsor>
        <funder>European Research Council - ERC</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor/>
        <availability status="free">
          <licence>Public domain</licence>
        </availability>
        <idno type="DOI"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>The hero is stuck between two contradictory orders</note>
        <note>Known under different titles (Tu chanteras, tu ne chanteras
          pas; Chantera, chantera pas…), this play is one of the
          classical Guignol texts. It is a part of the second installment of the
          Théâtre lyonnais de Guignol (The Guignol theatre from Lyon) published
          by Jean-Baptiste Onofrio in 1870, a collection of the plays written by Laurent
          Mourguet (1769-1844), the creator of Guignol, or by his descendants. Onofrio
          introduces the play as a farcical sketch that the troupe performed before the main
          show, as an introduction. The version described here is that of
          the oldest known manuscript, kept in the Musée Gadagne of Lyon in the funds Léopold
          Dor. It bears the initials of the Rhône subprefecture in Villefranche-sur-Saône,
          dated from December 11th, 1852. Victor-Napoléon Vuillerme Dunand wrote « author »
          next to his signature, as he did on every manuscript submitted to the subprefecture
          so that he could be allowed to perform them - but they are actually older texts, in
          the repertoire of the troupe of Laurent Mourguet’s descendants. It is impossible to
          determine when they were first played. Here, we only have the plot
          outlines with the principal lines and the stage directions. Comparisons with the
          versions published by Onofrio in 1870 or Gaston Baty in 1934 show how the play
          developed: running gags were emphasised, and actions were shortened and
          justified.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <personGrp role="audience">
            <p>Not specified</p>
          </personGrp>
        </listPerson>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>Collection Musées Gadagne - Ville de Lyon</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
            <physDesc>
              <objectDesc>
                <p>Number of pages in the original document: 3</p>
                <p>Number of acts in the original document: 1</p>
                <p>Format of the original document: Handwritten outline</p>
              </objectDesc>
            </physDesc>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
        <bibl>
          <title type="main">Tu chanteras, tu ne chanteras</title>
          <date>First half of the 19th century</date>
          <author>
            <persName>Vuillerme-Dunand Victor-Napoléon</persName>
            <idno type="IDREF">188286276</idno>
          </author>
          
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="fra">French</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords source="animationTechniques">
          <term source="https://puppetplays.eu/en/techniques-d-animation/521/glove-puppets">Glove-puppet</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="literaryTones">
          <term/>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="theatricalTechniques">
          <term>Running gag</term>
          <term>Song</term>
          <term>Dilemma</term>
          <term>Blow-with-a-stick</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="genre">
          <term>null</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords source="keywords">
          <term>Noise</term>
          <term>Illness</term>
          <term>Contradiction</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <normalization method="silent">
          <p>The semi-diplomatic norms applied are intended to guide and facilitate the reading of the original texts. The transcriptions therefore include spelling and grammatical corrections according to current standards.</p>
          <p>The author's orthographic and grammatical corrections have been integrated into the text without being marked. Cuts for performance purposes have not been adopted in the transcription.</p>
          <p>Syntax has been modernised where it is naturally incorrect or has become incomprehensible today. Additions are limited and indicated by square brackets.</p>
          <p>The copyist's obvious errors (scene numbers, character attributions, etc.) have been corrected. The list of characters could also be corrected.</p>
        </normalization>
        <punctuation marks="some">
          <p>Punctuation has been corrected according to modern rules.</p>
        </punctuation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Text collected during the PuppetPlays project funded by European Union (Grant
          Agreement 835193) under Horizon 2020. The PuppetPlays project aims to
          re-evaluate the contribution of the puppets repertoire to the construction of
          European cultural identity. Its main goals is to collect a corpus of
          representative plays from Western Europe (Germany, Austria, Belgium, Spain,
          France, Great Britain, Italy, Netherlands, Portugal, Switzerland) between the
          17th and the 21th century. It also tries to identify the characteristics of
          puppet dramaturgy and their variations depending on eras, cultural spheres,
          producing conditions, and the aimed public.</p>
        <p>This edition is the result of university research work, reviewed by the principal investigator.</p>
        <p>This transcription and the editorial work are distributed under the <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"> Creative
          Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA)
        </ref> licence. This license enables reusers to distribute, remix, adapt, and
          build upon the material in any medium or format for non-commercial purposes
          only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator. If you remix,
          adapt, or build upon the material, you must license the modified material under
          identical terms. </p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when-iso="2024-06-01" who="#PM">Text transcription.</change>
      <change when-iso="2025-04-29" who="#MSK">TEI Header created from a JSON extraction of the PuppetPlays' database.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb n="5" facs="19_F_VUILLERME-DUNAND_LaParisienne_FR_GAD_005.jpg"/>
      <docAuthor>
        <persName>Victor-Napoléon Vuillerme-Dunand</persName>
      </docAuthor>
      <docTitle>
        <titlePart type="main">Tu chanteras tu ne chanteras</titlePart>
      </docTitle>
      <docDate>Première moitié du 19e siècle</docDate>
      <castList>
        <head type="personnage">[Personnages</head>
        <castItem>
          <role>Le docteur,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Caporal,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Le militaire,</role>
        </castItem>
        <castItem>
          <role>Guignol]</role>
        </castItem>
      </castList>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="3">
        <head type="scene">[Scène 1]</head>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Le docteur</speaker>
          <p>Oui mon cher ami, je vous le répète, le moindre bruit peut la mettre en danger.
                  [Vous êtes]. Veillez-y !</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Caporal</speaker>
          <p>Soyez tranquille chère Poupoule, je vais prévenir mon domestique de veiller à ce
                  que personne ne chante ou crie sur le place.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">Ils sortent.</stage>
      </div>
      <div type="3">
        <head type="scene">[Scène 2]</head>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Le militaire</speaker>
          <p>En avant, marche bataillon. J'ai sauté quand jai revu tonton et le chemin ne m'a
                  pas semblé long. Il me reste encore deux lieux à faire pour embrasser ma bonne
                  mère et mes deux petites soeurs. Entrons là chez père Bajason.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">Il sort.</stage>
      </div>
      <div type="3">
        <head type="scene">Scène 3</head>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>Adieu, vieux grigoux, vieille asperge montée, vieux rossignol à gland. C'est vrai
                  ça, il me dit ce matin "Guignol apporte moi ma tasse tout de suite et je lui monte
                  sans faite". Attention un vieux pot de confiture, il croit que c'est pour me
                  moquer de lui, il me fait mon compte et me v'la sans le pavé ! Mais comme dit mon
                  bourgeaois quand j'ai de l'argent, je chante pour n'être pas triste, quand j'ai
                  pas le sous, je chante parce que je suis gay. <stage type="corps">(bis)</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Le militaire</speaker>
          <p>Tu chantes très bien l'ami et pour te récompenser, tiens voici cinq francs mais à
                  condition <pb n="6" facs="19_F_VUILLERME-DUNAND_LaParisienne_FR_GAD_006.jpg"/>que
                  tu chantes devant cette auberge le temps que j'y resterai, tu boiras tant que tu
                  voudras.</p>
          <stage type="saut">Il sort.</stage>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>Qu'est-ce que je vas donc lui canter. Ah ! Malbrough s'en vas s'en guerre mironton
                  mirontaine.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cadet</speaker>
          <p>Eh dites donc l'ami, taisez-vous, il y a quelqu'un de malade. </p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>D'abord ça vous regarde pas, on me paye pour chanter, je chanterai !</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cadet</speaker>
          <p>Ah ! L'on vous paye et combien vous donne-t-on ? </p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>Cent sous.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cadet</speaker>
          <p>Voici dix francs et taisez-vous sans cela vous aurez affaire à moi !</p>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">Il sort.</stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>À la bonne heure, il y en a tant qui me paye pour travailler, celui là me paye
                  pour rien faire. Je veux pas lui voler son argent.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">Il se couche.</stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Le militaire</speaker>
          <p>Comment il dort ? je vais te réveiller. <stage type="corps">(Il sort et rentre
                     avec un baton.)</stage> Garde à vous peloton ! Arme, joue, feu ! <stage type="corps">(Il le frappe.)</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>T'as appuyé trop fort sur la cachette imbécile !</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Le militaire</speaker>
          <p>Je t'ai payé pour chanter, tu chanteras !</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>Oui, qu'est-ce qui me ferait l'amitié de me dire ce qui se passe dans mon individu
                  depuis <pb n="7" facs="19_F_VUILLERME-DUNAND_LaParisienne_FR_GAD_007.jpg"/>huit
                  mois, je gémit, je soupire. Qu'est-ce qui se passe dans mon individu ?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Cadet</speaker>
          <stage type="pers">(Il vient doucement, regarde, sort et revient avec un
                  baton.)</stage>
          <p>Tiens ! <stage type="corps">(Il le frappe.)</stage></p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>Il m'a coupé le souffle.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Le militaire</speaker>
          <p>Chante ! </p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>Est-ce que vous prenez ma tête pour un enclume ?</p>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">Guignol se revenge et les frappe à son tour.</stage>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Le militaire</speaker>
          <p>Je suis content de toi, tu t'es bien défendu. Mon village est à deux lieues d'ici,
                  viens chez nous, tu seras le bienvenu là. Personne ne t'empecheras de chanter.
               </p>
        </sp>
        <sp>
          <speaker>Guignol</speaker>
          <p>Vous êtes un bon graçon, militaire. Soyez tranquille, je vous amuserai ! Partons,
                  militaire et vous verrez que vous ne serez pas faché.</p>
        </sp>
        <stage type="saut">Ils partent.</stage>
      </div>
      <div type="5">
        <head type="div5">Fin</head>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
